Deep River Lace Company Records 1990.0002
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Deep River Lace Company Records
undated, 1922-1983
1990.0002
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
36.7 Linear feet
The collection contains administrative and financial records, correspondence, patterns and samples documenting the later years of the last Leavers loom lace manufacturer in the state of Connecticut.
36.7 linear feet.
Deep River Lace Company.
History
Deep River Lace Company was the last lace manufacturer using the Leavers lace machines when it closed its doors in June 1990. Housed in a historic building in Deep River, Connecticut, the four partners -- Anne Denette, Stanley Jakiel, Leo Denette and Peter DeCarli -- were among the last of a group of skilled workers familiar with the older, and more labor intensive, process of lace-making. The company was bought in 1964 from the Arthur Smith family.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of administrative and financial information concerning company operations, mostly during the 1950s and 1960s, when the company was known as Arthur Smith Inc. and then, beginning in 1964, as the Deep River Lace Company. The collection also holds a large number of patterns used for making lace produced by the company.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Correspondence ( undated, 1953-1973 ) includes correspondence between the Deep River Lace Company and its vendors and clients, as well as with professional and community organizations. There is a small amount of correspondence (1955-1960) to Herbert Wheatley of Arthur Smith Inc., the predecessor company of Deep River Lace Company, from Lester or Jack Wiener of Wiener Laces Inc. of New York, New York, about sketches of patterns.
Series II: Reference and Information Files ( undated, 1922-1981 ) includes professional and industry publications concerned with employment and production issues.
Series III: Financial Records ( 1933-1968 ) include documentation of production costs.
Series IV: Production Records ( undated, 1956-1970 ) includes patterns, sketches and information on individual machines.
Series V: Photographs ( undated, 1983 ) contains 14 images of staff, production and products.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections in June 1990 by Peter DeCarli, president of the company. The piece work record (1957-1968) and a color photograph of the former owners (1964) were donated by the Museum of American Textile History in September 1990. A small donation of patterns, correspondence and publications was made in December 2011 by Felicia Jakiel, wife of one of the last owners of the company.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Administrative Records.; Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Textiles.; Correspondence.; Deep River (Conn.); Deep River (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Textiles.; Drawings.; Financial Records.; Lace and lace making--Connecticut.; Lace and lace making--Patterns.; Notebooks.; Patterns.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.; Sketches.; Swatches.
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1953-1973
  - A--General, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amalgamated Lace Operatives of America, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B--General, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C--General, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Connecticut Blue Cross, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Connecticut Medical Service, Inc., 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Connecticut, State of, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - D--General, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Deep River National Bank, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - E--General, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - F--General, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - G--General, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hartford Steam Boiler Inspection Company, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - I. Zendman, Inc., 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - J--General, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - John Jardine Limited, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - K--General, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - L--General, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Leavers Lace Manufacturers of America, Inc., 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - M--General, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Manufacturers Association of Connecticut, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - N--General, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - National Labor Relations Board, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - O--General, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - P--General, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - R--General, 1953-1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - S--General, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sterling Laces, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - T--General, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Tillinghast-Stiles Company, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Tunnicliffe Developments Ltd., 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - U-V--General, 1964-1967, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Valley Lace Company, 1964, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Vasiliou, William A., 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - W--General, undated, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Wiener Laces, Inc., 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 36, Box 46)
- Series II: Reference and Information Files, undated, 1922-1981
  - American Lace Worker, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Comparative Yarn Tables, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cotton Yarn Rules, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Directory of the American Lace Industry, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Levers Price List, 1922-1953 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Manufacturers Industrial Guide, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1952, 1978, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Wage Structure, 1949, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Yarn Inventory, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Publications on weaving leavers lace, 1949, 1957 (Box 47)
- Series III: Financial Records, 1933-1968
  - Ledger, 1933-1940 (Volume 3)
  - Ledger, 1933-1941 (Volume 4)
  - Production (piece work) record, 1957-1968 (Volume 5)
  - Petty cash record, 1964-1968 (Box 47)
- Series IV: Production Records, undated, 1956-1970
  - Machine Notebooks, 1956-1970
    - 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Price List for Merchandise, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Samples 4030-4249, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Samples, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Patterns, undated, 1958-1968
    - 11400 - 11409, 1958 (Folder 9)
    - 11410 - 11418, 1958-1959 (Folder 10)
    - 11419 - 11429, 1958 (Folder 11)
    - 11430 - 11435, 1958 (Folder 12)
    - 11436 - 11440, 1958 (Folder 13)
    - 11441 - 11447, 1958 (Folder 14)
    - 11447A - 11452, 1958 (Folder 15)
    - 11453 - 11455, 1958 (Folder 16)
    - 11476 - 11479, 1959 (Folder 17)
    - 11480 - 11489, 1959 (Folder 18)
    - 11490 - 11499, 1959 (Folder 19)
    - 11500 - 11505, 1959 (Folder 20)
    - 11507 - 11511, 1959 (Folder 21)
    - 11512 - 11518, 1959 (Folder 22)
    - 11523 - 11525, 1960 (Folder 23)
    - 11651 - 11653, 1962 (Folder 24)
    - 11655 - 11659, 1962 (Folder 25)
    - 11660A - 11665, 1962 (Folder 26)
    - 11666 - 11673, 1962 (Folder 27)
    - 11674 - 11678, 1962 (Folder 28)
    - 11679 - 11682, 1962 (Folder 29)
    - 11719 - 11720, 1967 (Folder 30)
    - 12000 - 12057, 1965 (Folder 31)
    - 12059 - 12062, 1965-1966 (Folder 32)
    - 12063 - 12067, 1966 (Folder 33)
    - 12068 - 12070, 1966 (Folder 34)
    - 12101 - 12104, 1967 (Folder 35)
    - 12105 - 12107, 1967 (Folder 36)
    - 12071 - 12108, 1966-1967 (Folder 37)
    - 12109 - 12111, 1968 (Folder 38)
    - 12112 - 12114, 1968 (Folder 39)
    - 12116 - 12120, 1968 (Folder 40)
    - 12/14310 - 12/32075, 1964-1968 (Folder 41)
    - Unnumbered, undated (Folder 42)
    - Incomplete, 11388, 21833, 7014, 1958-1965 (Folder 43)
  - Pattern Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Pattern Book, undated (Folder 1, Folder 55)
  - Pattern Book, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Pattern Book, undated (Volume 6)
  - Pattern Book, undated (Volume 7)
  - Sketches, undated (Folder 8)
  - Patterns, undated, 1955-1961 (Box 45)
  - Patterns, undated, 1955-1957 (Box 46)
  - Patterns, undated, 1964-1966 (Box 47)
- Series V: Photographs, undated, 1983
  - Photographs (14 items showing scenes of staff, production and products), undated, 1983 (Box 44)